

## **Summary**

I'm a PhD student at Universitat Pompeu Fabra under the joint supervision of Gemma Boleda and Laia Mayol. My PhD research currently focuses on understanding the use of referring expressions, mainly through quantitative and computational methods.

### Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

Ph.D. candidate in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics

2019 - present

**Universitat Pompeu Fabra** 

Barcelona, Spain

M.S. IN THEORETICAL AND APPLIED LINGUISTICS

2018 - 2019

• GPA: 8.68/10

· Venue: Computational Linguistics

#### Beijing Jiaotong University, Complutense University of Madrid

Beijing, China

B.S. IN HISPANIC PHILOLOGY

2014 - 2018

· GPA: 9.58/10

· with Honors

### **Publication**

Liao, X., Boleda, G., Mayol, L. (2021). Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data. Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung 26, to appear.

Aina, L., Liao, X., Boleda, G., Westera, M. (2021, November). Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution. In Proceedings of the 25th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (pp. 454-469).

#### **Presentation**

**UR-Ling workshop** Barcelona, Spain

TALK

November 12th, 2021

November 11th, 2021

• Title: Referent predictability and referential choice

#### The SIGNLL Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL) 2021

Virtually

POSTER PRESENTATION

European Summer School in Logic,

Language and Information (ESSLLI)

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [PDF], [Poster]

Sinn und Bedeutung 26 Virtually

TALK

September 9th. 2021

· Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

## Workshop on Computational and Experimental Explanations in Semantics and **Pragmatics**

2021, Virtually August 10th. 2021

TALK

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

#### Student session in European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021

Virtually

August 6th. 2021

TALK

· Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

XIXIAN LIAO · RÉSUMÉ NOVEMBER 20, 2021



#### Semàntica i Pragmàtica

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

2020 - 2021

**TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR MASTER COURSES** 

- Compositionality and Truth(conditions)
- Modality and possible worlds; Quantifiers
- · Clausal and nominal reference
- Presuppositions
- The Gricean program. Recognizing intentions.
- What we do when we use language: Speech act theory.
- Dynamic theories of meaning. Language in interaction.
- · Expressing emotions and other non-truth-conditional meaning.
- The relation between language, thought and communication

#### Introducció a la Universitat i Recursos

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

**TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR UNDERGRADUATE COURSES** 

- Build an HTML website
- · Regular expressions
- · Corpus analysis

2020 - 2022

## Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

#### China's Commerce Ministry, Beijing Jiaotong University Training Center

Beijing, China

CHINESE-SPANISH INTERPRETER & TRANSLATOR IN SEMINARS FOR FOREIGN DELEGATIONS

2017 - 2018

- Bilateral Seminar of Infrastructure Between China and Uruguay.
- Seminar On Ocean Railway Construction for Perú-Brasil

**Cielo Education** Beijing, China

CHINESE TEACHER FOR FOREIGNERS • Teaching elementary Chinese. 2017 - 2018

# **Fellowships**

2020.5-2023.5 FI Scholarship awarded by AGAUR (Agency for Management of University and Research Grants) 2019.9-2020.5 CSC Scholarship awarded by Chinese Scholarship Council

## Languages & Skills

LANGUAGES Mandarin Chinese (native), English (IELTS C1), Spanish (DELE C1) SKILLS Python, R, HTML, Visual Basic

## **Membership in Scientific Association**

Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)

2021 - present